<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>God, a rich supply of all good Setting forth, I. The beleevers interest in it. II. The riches of it in quantity. III. The gloriousnesse of it in quality. IV. The meanes of sealing up all: namely, Christ. All illustrated, with many wonderfull and remarkable spirituall experiences, not onely of former, but of later Christians. By Doctor Nathanael Homes.</title>
            <author>Homes, Nathanael, 1599-1678.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1650</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 47 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A86499</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H2565</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1341_3</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R209144</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99868035</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99868035</idno>
            <idno type="VID">120372</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A86499)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 120372)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 177:E1341[3])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>God, a rich supply of all good Setting forth, I. The beleevers interest in it. II. The riches of it in quantity. III. The gloriousnesse of it in quality. IV. The meanes of sealing up all: namely, Christ. All illustrated, with many wonderfull and remarkable spirituall experiences, not onely of former, but of later Christians. By Doctor Nathanael Homes.</title>
                  <author>Homes, Nathanael, 1599-1678.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>31, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by Tho: Roycroft, in Gold-smiths Alley neer Creple Gate,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1650.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Issued with his "Dæmonologie, and theologie" (which has separate pagination and register)?.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy of "Dæmonologie, and theologie": "Nou: 4th".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Philippians --  Commentaries --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Christian life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>God --  Goodness --  Meditations --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:120372:1"/>
            <p>GOD, A rich ſupply OF ALL GOOD. SETTING FORTH,</p>
            <list>
               <item>I. The Beleevers intereſt in it.</item>
               <item>II. The riches of it in quantity.</item>
               <item>III. The gloriouſneſſe of it in quality.</item>
               <item>IV. The meanes ſealing up all: Namely,</item>
            </list>
            <p>CHRIST. All illuſtrated, with many won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull and remarkable ſpirituall experiences, not onely of former, but of later Chriſtians.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By Doctor</hi> NATHANAEL HOMES.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Tho: Roycroft,</hi> in Gold-ſmiths Alley neer Creple Gate, 1650.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:120372:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:120372:2"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>PHILIP. 4.19.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>But my GOD ſhall ſupply all your need, according to his riches in glory, by Chriſt Jeſus.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>ERE is a <hi>rich</hi> and <hi>glorious</hi> Text; for it containes <hi>riches</hi> and <hi>glory. A comprehenſive</hi> Text, for it holds forth a <hi>ſupply of all need.</hi> The <hi>Fountaine</hi> is infinite, <hi>Viz. God. God</hi> ſhall thus <hi>ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply.</hi> The <hi>conveyance</hi> and inſurance infallible, <hi>Chriſt Jeſus.</hi> And the <hi>impreſſion</hi> that all theſe make upon the heart of a Beleever firſt or laſt, is very great. For this Text is ſpoken out of much confidence, and <hi>experience: My God ſhall ſupply.</hi> My God that hath ſupplyed <hi>me, Verſ.</hi> 12, 13. ſhall ſupply <hi>you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So that the <hi>But</hi> in our Engliſh tranſlation, may be better turned into <hi>And</hi> (as the Greek well beares it) thus: God hath heretofore ſupplyed me, <hi>Verſ.</hi> 13. now you have ſupplyed me, <hi>Verſ.</hi> 14, 16. AND <hi>God ſhall ſupply you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu.</hi> Why did not <hi>Paul</hi> refuſe the <hi>Philippians</hi> benevolence, and turne YOUR into MY, and his <hi>words</hi> to others, into <hi>Faith</hi> for himſelfe, ſaying, My God ſhall ſupply all <hi>my need.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ. Paul</hi> could, and hath, and would againe have done this, if God had denyed all meanes, but
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:120372:3"/>for him to refuſe means, when meanes are offered, had been to tempt God, not to truſt in him. The <hi>Philippians</hi> had well to ſpare, and (contrary to the gripple <hi>Corinthians</hi>) were willing to ſpare; and <hi>Pauls</hi> hands could not make up his <hi>need;</hi> hee muſt fulfill his Miniſtry, what ever was layd by, and he had been rich in Doctrines to the <hi>Philip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pians,</hi> therefore the <hi>Philippians</hi> did well to give, and he did well to receive. Beſides <hi>Pauls</hi> Faith here ingageth for more to the <hi>Philippians,</hi> then his <hi>ſenſe</hi> had received. He, one, had received from them a great many, ſome ſmall contribution of ſome temporall things; but hee promiſeth them that his God ſhould ſupply all the need of them all, ſpiritually and temporally. <hi>My God ſhall ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply all your</hi> NEED, <hi>according to his riches by Chriſt Jeſus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Shall ſupply,</hi> Greek <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>ſhall fill,</hi> or <hi>will fill.</hi> He <hi>ſhall,</hi> becauſe he will. His <hi>good will</hi> puts a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity on his great <hi>power</hi> to doe great things for his people. See the great things, the fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals of ſalvation, of grace and glory that God doth for his in and by Chriſt Jeſus, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1. firſt ten Verſes. And Why? Becauſe he had taken <hi>counſell with his will</hi> ſo to doe, <hi>Verſ.</hi> 13. So in all Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences, yea in all things, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.28, 29. Mark well the FOR that knits the two Verſes together. And as his will is a <hi>good will,</hi> ſo <hi>a rich</hi> good will. <hi>Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his riches</hi> (ſaith the Text.) He is <hi>rich</hi> for our <hi>need;</hi> and hath <hi>riches</hi> for every need. And
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:120372:3"/>
               <hi>richly</hi> ſhall he proportion the allowance <hi>viz. Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his riches in glory.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The adjoining <hi>glory</hi> to <hi>riches</hi> ſignifies (as ſom, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Beza,</hi> will) that God wil ſupply according to his riches <hi>gloriouſly;</hi> or rather it ſignifies more, to wit, that he will ſupply according to his <hi>glorious riches.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For all the ſupplyes that come from God through Chriſt to one in Chriſt, come tipt, guilt, with a glory upon them; <hi>a centro ad caelum.</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidences below, graces within, Heaven above, as they have a lovely ſcarlet bluſh of Chriſts blood upon them, ſo they are rayed upon with a beame of divine love to them that are in Chriſt.</p>
            <p>And whether we render the text <hi>in</hi> Chriſt, or <hi>by</hi> Chriſt, or with Chriſt, it makes no great matter, ſee the Scripturs. For according to Scripture all are true, and apt, yea all will well concur to make forth the all of the way, how all things are ours through Chriſt. In regard of Chriſts <hi>Paſſion,</hi> we have all <hi>by</hi> Chriſt; namely by purchaſe. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.11.12. In regard of Chriſts <hi>incarnation,</hi> we have all <hi>in</hi> Chriſt, namely in our union with him, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.5. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 15.5. <hi>Coloſ.</hi> 2.10. In regard of <hi>dona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> we have all <hi>with</hi> Chriſt. That is God giving us Chriſt in ſpirituall marriage, with him he gives all he is worth, all his eſtate with him. <hi>Tranſit res cum perſona. Rom.</hi> 8.32.</p>
            <p>D. Beleivers have aſſurance and experience that their God will fully ſupply all their need accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to his glorious riches through Chriſt Jeſus.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:120372:4"/>
            <p> There are 4 things to be explained in order as they lye in the doctrine for the manifeſtation, and ſo confirmation thereof. 1 The beleivers <hi>intereſt</hi> in the Supplyer, that makes him ſo bold and confident as to ſay, <hi>My God ſhall do ſo and ſo.</hi> 2 The <hi>exten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion</hi> in <hi>quantity</hi> of the ſupply: to ſupply <hi>all need.</hi> 3 The intenſion in quallity, <hi>According to his glorious riches.</hi> 4 The medium or means, <hi>Chriſt Jeſus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. The <hi>intereſt.</hi> The beleiver hath a God, the onely true God, truly; who is the originall of all. All goodneſſes but coppies taken out of, and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to that originall. All ſtreames of goodneſſe are from that Ocean of <hi>Nectar.</hi> All my ſprings (ſaith the <hi>Pſalmiſt Pſal.</hi> 87. <hi>ult.</hi>) are in thee. <hi>i.e.</hi> From God giving forth himſelfe in the Church. All things are in God, either <hi>formally</hi> or <hi>cauſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> or <hi>eminently.</hi> Wiſedom, power, &amp;c. are ſo <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mally</hi> in God, that they are <hi>eſſentially</hi> God. All the creatures are <hi>cauſally</hi> in God. That is, they have moving and being from an efficacy proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from him. And all the reſt are <hi>eminently</hi> in God; whatſoever is excellent below; is in God in a more excellent manner. As light is more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent in the Sun, then in the fire or candle. God is the divine <hi>Artiſt</hi> to know all. He is the divine <hi>Artificer, facere</hi> to make, all. Heb. 11. And he is the divine <hi>vertuous one, Agere,</hi> to do all. As it is ſaid of Chriſt, <hi>he did all things well. Acti agimus</hi> we act well, being well acted of him. His <hi>omnipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent power</hi> upholds all. <hi>His all-loving heart</hi> gives
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:120372:4"/>all. And his <hi>allwiſe-hand</hi> diſpenceth all. His power is above all difficulties. And his good will above all our unworthyneſſe. You ſee the world below is vertually in the Sun; and the Sun a more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent thing then al on which it hath an influence: So all things are much more eminently in God, but God himſelfe is more excellent then all. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 84.11. His nature is unacceſſable. <hi>He dwels in light that none can approach unto.</hi> His love incomprehenſible. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 3. And his <hi>wayes</hi> of works and providences <hi>paſt finding out, Rom.</hi> 11. He ſupplyeth the Angels with power that fell not, that they might never fall. He ſupplyed Chriſt; filling him with <hi>the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit above meaſure,</hi> and <hi>raiſing him from the dead.</hi> Therefore much more can he ſupply us that Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leive.</p>
            <p>In this God, hath the beleiver his intereſt, he can confidently call him <hi>my God; mine</hi> by <hi>creation.</hi> And not onely of <hi>being,</hi> as the lapſed Angels, but of his <hi>well being,</hi> of a gracious heart, and gracious quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties in that heart, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51.10. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.24. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.10. <hi>Mine</hi> by <hi>preſervation,</hi> and not onely in <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon providences,</hi> as he is the Saviour of all men; but in preſervation of the ſoule from ſin, of the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections from prevayling temptations, and graces from deadneſſe. <hi>Mine</hi> by <hi>redemption.</hi> Sutably to that ſpecially here meant, is here mention of <hi>Chriſt Jeſus.</hi> According to that, <hi>Chriſt is made of God to us redemption;</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. He hath payd a price to juſtice to redeem us from vengeance; and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:120372:5"/>hath gained the actual love of mercy to beſtow all good upon us. * The ſame Fine and Recovery cuts of the entayle of evill, and conveighes the good eſtate to us. Upon theſe grounds, and in this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner doth the beleiver challenge God to be <hi>his God.</hi> If you will have the meaſure and graduall; then thus. The beleiver ſaith, God is my God, <hi>funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentally</hi> by the promiſe. As that, <hi>I will be your God,</hi> and <hi>you ſhall be my people. Formally</hi> and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly by faith, <hi>my beloved is mine,</hi> and I am his. <hi>Cant.</hi> 2. And <hi>Thomas, my Lord and my God. Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually,</hi> and feelingly, by the operations of love, joy, &amp;c. As <hi>Mary</hi>-ſayd, <hi>my ſpirit hath rejoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced in God my Saviour.</hi> And as the beleiving <hi>Iewes</hi> did. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.8. <hi>Compleatly,</hi> (in parts) when we own God, and own our ſelves to be none but his. Faith drawing down Chriſt to us. And that faith working by love, carryes us up to Chriſt. <hi>Cant.</hi> 2, <hi>My BELOVED is mine, and I am HIS, he feed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth among the Lillies, untill the day breake, and the ſhaddowes flee away, turn my beloved, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 <hi>Extenſion in quantity.</hi> God ſhall ſupply, even <hi>to a fulſilling all needs.</hi> The word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, here ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered <hi>need:</hi> 1. Signifies want, neceſſity. So that whatſoever is neceſſary to ſupply, God will ſupply. A <hi>ſinleſſe</hi> wanting, <hi>viz.</hi> of ſuch things without which we cannot anſwer to Gods ends, God will be ſure to ſupply. But a <hi>ſinfull</hi> wanting, a moral aguiſh dropſy thirſt of ſuch things, and ſo much, as will rather hurt then help; a <hi>wantonneſſe</hi> rather
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:120372:5"/>then a <hi>want,</hi> God doth beſt ſupply rather by keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing us in that want then ſupplying; rather by withholding then by giving. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119. <hi>It is good for me that I was afflicted.</hi> For in this caſe we more want ſoule health then bodily ſupplyes; therefore God withholding the drink of creature-comforts, is beſt to cure our ſpiritual ague or dropſie appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tite. So then our deſires muſt be natural, not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natural, either after things in kinde, not good <hi>for us,</hi> or in degrees unſutable for our condition. As on the otherſide our wanting muſt be real, not ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginary as the dream of thirſt in the Prophet. Such an imaginary want was in <hi>Rachel</hi> when ſhe phanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſied that her life depended upon having children. <hi>Give me children (ſayd ſhe) or I dye.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The Greek word ſignifies <hi>uſe,</hi> that which is <hi>uſefull,</hi> and inſtrumental to act and doe. Now that is for our true uſe, that more fits us for Gods uſe. For (as the Philoſopher called Servants) we are Gods, <hi>inſtrumenta rationalia;</hi> his reaſonable tools or houſhold goods. <hi>Revel.</hi> 4. All is made for Gods end and uſe; Therefore without all faile God will ſo ſupply and ſerve our need, as may fit us beſt to ſerve him. And in relation to both ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifications of the Word, remember that I told you that the word <hi>ſupply</hi> in the original, ſignifies to <hi>fill;</hi> God will at leaſt <hi>fill</hi> the true uſeful need. He may and doth oft make our <hi>cup to overflow,</hi> gives <hi>a mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure running over;</hi> but that is of ſuperabundant kindneſſe. But this he will do, and is, tyed under
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:120372:6"/>hand and ſeale, in Word and Sacraments; <hi>viz.</hi> to <hi>fill</hi> ſuch wants. He will <hi>fill</hi> every ſize of veſſel, repleniſh every capacity to its proportion. He will ballaſt and tackle every ſhip, as it may ſafelyeſt ſwim and ride out every ſtorme. He clothes lambs and ſheep with a fleece they may beſt bear, and get away from the thornes.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Intention</hi> in qualities, one way or other, firſt or laſt he will <hi>ſupply</hi> according to his <hi>glorious riches.</hi> God is glorious, and ſo will dole out your ſhare according to your proportion, you ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe it when the total is caſt up. In compariſon of others <hi>nothing,</hi> or your own former <hi>ſmall</hi> thing, you ſhall have great things. <hi>God hath choſen the poore in regard of the world,</hi> (ſaith <hi>Iames</hi>) <hi>rich in faith.</hi> And (ſaith <hi>Paul</hi>) <hi>Godlineſſe is great gaine with contentment.</hi> For it brings contentment, hearts eaſe; more ſatisfied then <hi>Alexander</hi> with a world. The Godly man hath two worlds entayled upon him. <hi>Godlineſſe hath the promiſe of this world, and that to come.</hi> So that the Godly man can ſay, <hi>I have enough;</hi> He is rich that thinks he wants no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing; that hath as much as he can aske, or tell what well to doe with; give us, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, bread ſufficient for our ſubſtance. A mans eſtate is to be valued according to the uſe, not the bulke, according to the efficacy not the quantity. What are tooles of which one hath no uſe or benefit? <hi>Green hearbs if they give content</hi> (ſaith <hi>Solomon</hi>) <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed a ſtalled Oxe.</hi> If a mans eſtate ſerve his uſe,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:120372:6"/>is effectual to a quietation of ſpirit, he hath the greateſt ENOUGH that can be deſired.</p>
            <p>The whole of a beleivers eſtate is very rich, thus:
<list>
                  <item>1. The leaſt <hi>mercy</hi> is greater then he (as <hi>Iacob</hi> confeſſed) for a man is all <hi>miſery</hi> in himſelfe.</item>
                  <item>2. The leaſt that he hath, as to him, that it might be a mercy (not a ſnare) coſt the value of Chriſts blood. A little Diamond coſts more then a load of quarry ſtones.</item>
                  <item>3. If the ſtream of mercies be ſmall, yet great is the continuance, from the fountaine. A little free-hold is better then more by ſhort leaſe.</item>
                  <item>4. Beſides all, he hath the fountaine it ſelfe; God himſelfe. The heavenly man, hath not onely the light, but the Sun it ſelfe fixed in him as in its Orb. The Chriſtian and God are one, as Chriſt and God are one. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 14.20. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 17.21. All that God gives to beleivers, intends, &amp; ends in this, to lead them to God. (Judge your condition by this) God is a wooer, that gives tokens to his love with an intent to give himſelfe.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>You ſee then God doth many wayes ſupply <hi>richly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That richneſſe according to which God will ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply is a <hi>glorious</hi> richneſſe. The glory is three-fold; as the riches are three-fold.</p>
            <p n="1">1. There is a glory upon the <hi>temporalls</hi> of a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leiver. They come from Gods <hi>right hand.</hi> See the difference, <hi>Pro.</hi> 3. and in the Patriarks bleſſing.
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:120372:7"/>The right hand bleſſings perfected the left. They come from Gods good wil, not from meer com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon providence. They all taſte loviſh; they are varniſhed with love; poliſhed with a beauty as given to Chriſt for us, as the world was made ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding good; that is, beautiful, uſeful, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> for the firſt <hi>Adam</hi> in innocency. Again, there is a glory in the ſeaſonable giving of temporals to beleivers, So <hi>like apples of gold with picturs of ſilver.</hi> Striped with the blood of Chriſt, inlayed with the opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſpirit ſanctifying them unto us. Yea, there is ſomewhat of God himſelfe ſtamped upon every creature, which onely the beleeving eye can ſee. On vegetables, <hi>life,</hi> on <hi>Animals,</hi> underſtanding and wiſdome. And ſo much of God as is in a creature is moſt glorious. And God that is in them hath layd his Command upon them, to doe us good (if we beleive) and goodneſſe is glorious.</p>
            <p>If there were but the divine order in Gods diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſations of outward things, firſt this, then that as is beſt for our welfare; this were glorious. He firſt provides for us the breaſt, then bread. He diſpenſeth as the parent doth clothes, ſuites fit for our age, and ſo they ſit handſomely. Look how grimme diſorder is, ſo comely and glorious is or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. He gives not all at once to over-whelm us; nor the laſt thing firſt, or the firſt laſt.</p>
            <p n="2">2. There is a glory in ſpirituals. In <hi>gifts</hi> ſome as in knowledge, elocution, &amp;c. but in grace and
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:120372:7"/>graces more. For the <hi>grace</hi> of favour; It clothes us with Chriſts righteouſneſſe: This muſt needs be glorious. (2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. <hi>la</hi>) it being <hi>the righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of God.</hi> You may perceive it, by conſidering how grimme the ſight of ſin was to you, before you ſaw that glorious clothing upon you. Whiles ye ſee not your ſelves in Chriſt, mantled in, and clothed with his righteouſneſſe, you are an abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to your ſelves. But when you behold your ſelves (yea and as beheld of God in Chriſts righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe) you ſee your glory, ſo that you can glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. two la. <hi>Chriſt is made to us righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>that he that glorieth may glory in the Lord.</hi> The Apoſtle adds, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. that the very miniſtry that holds forth this righteouſneſſe to us is far more glorious then the glorious giving of that glorious <hi>fierie Law,</hi> as it is ſet forth and cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, <hi>Deut.</hi> 33.2. <hi>The Lord came from Sinai, and roſe up from Seir, and ſhone forth from mount Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ran, and he came with ten thouſand of his Saints, from his right hand went a FIERIE Law for them.</hi> And then too, the <hi>graces</hi> of the Saints are glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous. They are the ſpiritual <hi>creation</hi> of God. <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.10. The <hi>purchaſe of Chriſts</hi> blood, <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.7, 8. The <hi>breathings of the Spirit, Ioh.</hi> 20.22. The <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of God</hi> in us. <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.24. They make the ſoule of man (in the bent of it) like <hi>Adams</hi> ſoule; yea it is another divine ſoule, in our natural ſoule.</p>
            <p>So that by all glories aforeſayd, a Saint is made
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:120372:8"/>moſt glorious within his own court or habitation. He dwels in Chriſt, glorious in his garments, glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious in his complexion; he is ful of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and holineſſe. <hi>Solomon</hi> was glorious; the Lillies (ſaith Chriſt) are more glorious then he, but Chriſt moſt glorious; and ſpiritually and imputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively, <hi>as he was, ſo are we in this world.</hi> 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 4.17.</p>
            <p n="3">3. There is the glory of <hi>heaven;</hi> which is the plat-forme of all our happineſſe. I need not argue this glory, but rather declare it, if I (or any elſe) could. Here below we have a glory, but it is like the glory of a glow-worme, brightened at the night-ſhining of the ſtars, in compariſon of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, which is as the glaring of Diamonds, or ſpark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of Chryſtal looking-glaſſes, the gloſſe of cloth of gold, and Tiſſu, at the ſight of the noon-ſun. In heaven every glory is lightened and hightened to a tranſcendency of tranſlucidation and luſtre. Our natural bodies ſhall glitter above the face of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, Stephen,</hi> or innocent <hi>Adam;</hi> namely, like the body of Chriſt, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. which was moſt glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous on <hi>Tabor.</hi> Our reaſon ſhall be equalized too, if not made ſuperlative above the higheſt intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectuals of Angels (foraſmuch as we are neerer in union with God through Chriſt they.) And as for our graces, every grace ſhall be raiſed to the higheſt perfection, and actings that graces can be extended, or exalted. There in glory, we have
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:120372:8"/>the ſight of God; either by ſome extraordinary Species repreſenting the divine eſſence, a light of glory the mean while elevating the underſtanding with a ſupernatural ſtrength, to behold the repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentation; or by the light of glory, elevating and ſtrengthening the underſtanding to the higheſt, pitch of apprehenſion, to behold the divine eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence immediately preſented without any Species, or by any immediate clear viſion of God without. Species or elevation by any light, more then is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate in the glorified intellectuals. Doubtleſſe by unſpeakable union with Chriſt, in him we ſhall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend God, as he (ſo far forth as he is man) doth apprehend him, to our utmoſt proportion.</p>
            <p>In heaven the fountain of our happineſſe is ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantial glory. Namely, God himſelfe, perfecting our ſubſtances to the higheſt of our kinde; our company the Angels, ful of ſuperlative glorious qualities, the place filled with rayes of both, and we perfected and poliſhed in all things to a glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous hue and luſter. The floure coloured ſhining ſpring, the Golden ſea (as <hi>Homer</hi> calls it) with morning beames, or the ſpangſed ſtarry heavens, in a ſerene evening, are but ſhaddows to this glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in Heaven. Our communion there is like the moſt raviſhing muſick, our ſights all of admiration, and our thoughts ſeraphical raptures.</p>
            <p>The fourth thing to be explained is, the <hi>means, viz. Chriſt Jeſus.</hi> God conſidered in himſelf, is able to
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:120372:9"/>ſupply, being infinite rich and glorious. And <hi>na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally</hi> he is willing as the chiefe good to commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate his goodneſs to his creatures, conſidered in their meer and pure naturals; but there is not in him <hi>a moral</hi> willingneſſe (as we may ſay) a wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingneſſe of free choiſe to be communicative of himſelfe to fallen man, but through Jeſus Chriſt. God foreſeeing what was wiſedome and juſtice to himſelfe, choſe us in Chriſt. And now in time com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municates himſelfe no other way, but through Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt. He is fixt in, and ſhines through the Orbe of Chriſt Jeſus, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. <hi>Shines to us in the face of Chriſt Jeſus;</hi> even as after the Sun was made upon the fourth day, (though there was ſome general light afore, as innocent <hi>Adam</hi> had a legal light) there was no light to be communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the world but through the Sun. The ſum of all we wil ſay of this is briefly this.
<list>
                  <item>1. That Chriſts <hi>incarnation</hi> is the <hi>fundamental inſurance</hi> of our aſſurance of our neererneſſe to God then Angels, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2. That he wil be our <hi>Immanuel. Matth.</hi> 1. Applyed, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. to our juſtification and ſalvation. And ſo wil doe by us as he did by Chriſt, in all excellencies whereof we may be ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable.</item>
                  <item>2. The <hi>perfecting and formal act</hi> of the vertue of this <hi>incarnation</hi> to communicate himſelfe to us, is our <hi>actual union with Chriſt by the Spirit.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. That Chriſt is the <hi>pattern</hi> to which we muſt in all things, according to our proportion be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:120372:9"/>to; and is the <hi>beginning of the reaſſimila<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting</hi> and making us like to Gods image in the firſt Innocent <hi>Adam,</hi> Chriſt therefore is called, the <hi>firſt borne of every creature, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Uſeful is this Doctrine, 1. For <hi>invitation</hi> of all that ſtand off at a <hi>difference</hi> with Chriſt, total<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly holding off, or ſtand off at a <hi>diſtance</hi> from Chriſt, as in a degree ſtrange, fearing to come neer and cloſe to Chriſt; in doubt whether to throw them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves into Chriſts armes, fully to truſt themſelves with him. Come ſaith this Doctrine, come in, come neer, own God in Chriſt, and rejoyce in him as thine own, that thou maiſt come up to this pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge, <hi>viz.</hi> with aſſurance of faith to ſay, <hi>My God ſhall ſupply all wants. Mine</hi> and <hi>thine</hi> in tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porals, ſet all the world together by the ears; Kings ſay, that is mine, nay ſay Parliaments, that is mine; nay ſay the people, that is mine. But in ſpirituals they ſet all in tune. Therefore of all things learne to MINE the Lord, to cry by faith, thou art <hi>mine,</hi> as <hi>Thomas, My Lord and my God;</hi> and as <hi>Mary, My God and my Saviour.</hi> You may as they (but more ſpiritually) rely on him, for you have him held forth to you not onely as <hi>borne,</hi> but as <hi>cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied</hi> for you before your eyes. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.1. That is, in the preaching of the Goſpel; which continual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>beſeecheth us</hi> to receive Chriſt. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. Why therefore do not men come in and come up cloſer to Chriſt Jeſus, through whom God will be ſuch a
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:120372:10"/>rich ſupply? And therefore if ye be <hi>poore</hi> like <hi>Laodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cea,</hi> it is becauſe ye do not com on through profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Chriſt cloſe to Chriſt himſelfe. If ye be <hi>rich,</hi> yet ye are not rich indeed, if ye cloſe not with Chriſt. If ye be <hi>honourable;</hi> yet ye are not <hi>right hon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ourable,</hi> unleſſe ye put on Chriſt. Come therefore, come, come to God in Chriſt. Hear thoſe glorious invitations, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 55.1. to the end of the Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. And <hi>Revel.</hi> 22.17. turn to them, reade them, weigh them; they wooe thee imphatically and pathetically; and anſwer all ſcruples. Come there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to Chriſt. <hi>The promiſe is to you,</hi> for it is <hi>to all the Lord ſhall call;</hi> that is to all that obey his Call, <hi>Act.</hi> 2.39. <hi>He dyed for the ungodly, Rom.</hi> 5. And he came with an intent <hi>not to condemne the world, but that the world might be ſaved, Joh.</hi> 3.</p>
            <p>Oh therefore cloſe with Chriſt, throw your ſelves into his armes. Let thine heart ſay, he is mine by faith, mine in hope; I love him, I give up my ſelfe to him, I will lye in his armes, lean on his boſome, live in and upon his heart of love, there I will expect all incomes from God. Cloſe with God in Chriſt, for here in the Text and Doctrine he doth as it were call to you in the marker place of wiſdome, <hi>come ſee what ye lack, ſee what ye want,</hi> do ye want riches, honour, comfort, any thing, all things, <hi>See what ye want, come buy,</hi> and buy with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out money or moneys worth. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 55.1. <hi>Revel.</hi> 22.27. And in the Text. <hi>He will ſupply all your
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:120372:10"/>wants.</hi> Do ye want a comfortable <hi>habitation? Pſ.</hi> 90.1. <hi>Lord thou haſt been our dwelling place in all generations.</hi> Do ye want <hi>riches? Solomon</hi> tells you <hi>The bleſſing of the Lord maketh rich.</hi> And <hi>Paul</hi> tells you that <hi>Godlineſſe is great gaine.</hi> And ſo we might run over all things, His <hi>power</hi> ſhall be your chambers to <hi>hide</hi> in, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 26.20. His <hi>love</hi> and u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion ſhall be your chamber (your Bride chamber) to <hi>rejoyce</hi> in. <hi>Cant.</hi> 1.4. Do ye want <hi>peace.</hi> The Apoſtle calls God, the <hi>God of peace.</hi> And he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſeth, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 26.3. <hi>He will keep them in perfect peace, whoſe mindes are ſtayd on him.</hi> Do ye want <hi>friends?</hi> By <hi>Faith Abraham was called the friend of God;</hi> that is, paſſively God was a friend to him; for <hi>God juſtified him by faith, Jam.</hi> 2.25. And by obedience (flowing from faith) we manifeſt we are <hi>Chriſts friends, Joh.</hi> 15.24. Do ye want <hi>wiſedome?</hi> And what to do? To bear afflictions (that perhapps ariſe from wants)? <hi>If any man lack wiſedome,</hi> (and for ſuch a purpoſe) <hi>let him ask it of God who gives it liberally. Jam.</hi> 1.</p>
            <p>If any man out of a willingneſſe to follow Chriſt <hi>looſeth all,</hi> he ſhall <hi>finde all,</hi> with addition above that he loſt. <hi>Matth.</hi> 19.28, 29.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> For ſpirituals, God doth eaſily ſupply them, by immediate infuſion. But how can he ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply temporal, when they are not in being?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> This is our fault. God provided <hi>Manna;</hi> But ſay they, can he provide <hi>fleſh</hi> in the Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe?
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:120372:11"/>Sure ſaith that great man, 2 <hi>Kin.</hi> 7.2. he cannot ſend plenty into beſieged <hi>Samaria,</hi> by to morrow, <hi>if the windows of heaven ſhould rain down bread.</hi> This or the like, is the language of our un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beleeving hearts, and the cenſures we paſſe upon divine providence, as if we would provoke God to do nothing for us. Why, God hath, and can do ſtrange things, ſo that they ſeem to be done by creation. How wonderfully did he lead his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple from <hi>Egypt</hi> into <hi>Canaan.</hi> And he will <hi>create Hieruſalem</hi> (a ſad City) into <hi>joy.</hi> He will <hi>create peace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Come therefore yee diſputers, attend upon the words of his mouth, rely on him by faith, he will be true, he muſt be true to you, according to this Text, <hi>To ſupply all your wants according to his rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es in glory by Chriſt Jeſus.</hi> Can ye finde a want, a need of ſpirituals? Do ye feele your need? <hi>Seek firſt the Kingdome of God, and the righteouſneſſe of him, and all other things ſhall be added unto you.</hi> Go cloſe with Chriſt, and then go to God and aske and have any thing that you truly need that may do you good. By this you ſhall know whether your outward wants be a true and right <hi>need,</hi> by what and how ye dare aske them of God in prayer. <hi>That</hi> is not a true <hi>need</hi> which you dare not ask boldly of God in prayer. And ſo <hi>much</hi> is not <hi>needful</hi> which you dare not confidently begge of God in prayer. And that <hi>way</hi> or <hi>manner,</hi> or <hi>meanes</hi> of attaining
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:120372:11"/>any thing is not <hi>needful,</hi> for which you dare not with a free heart petition to God for his bleſſing on the ſame. When God <hi>hath a minde to bend his eare,</hi> he will <hi>prepare the heart</hi> to pray. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 10.17. Therefore go to God by faith, make your addreſſes to him by prayer in faith for a <hi>ſupply</hi> of whatſoever ye <hi>need.</hi> Say here it is, here it is to be had, I wil go no further then this doore, here I wil ſtay, and begg till I receive.</p>
            <p>The Devil, and ſin wil tel us they wil ſupply our <hi>need,</hi> ſo they told the Angels (that fel) and <hi>Adam, Belzebub</hi> ſeduced the reſt, and one of them ſeduced <hi>Adam.</hi> The politick world wil bear us in hand, that they wil ſupply all our <hi>need.</hi> Do but come (ſay they) over to us, go our way, come plot in our Plot, co-operate, and comply in our deſigne and ye are made, we wil make you men for ever. And the creatures with their beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful looks wil ſmilingly ſeeme to promiſe much: And our owne corrupt hearts, and carnal reaſons wil tell us many faire tales. But whom and with what wil theſe ſupply? onely our ſenſes with ſenſible things, and leave our inward man to faint and faile; or they wil ſupply our luſts, with impure objects, which are worſe then no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, to poiſon and pain us to all degrees of mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery. They wil ſupply (they ſay) but according to what? even quite contrary to the text. <hi>viz.</hi> they wil ſupply according to the <hi>abundance and
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:120372:12"/>baſeneſſe of evil,</hi> that is in ſin, and the Devil. But the voice of the text is life, the voice of God in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed. <hi>He will ſupply all your need according to the riches of his glory by Chriſt Jeſus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Second Uſe is, for improvement of God in Chriſt Jeſus unto all conſolation, to them that can cloſely cloſe with, and own God in Chriſt: to ſay, <hi>My God</hi> by the blood of Chriſt, <hi>My God</hi> by the ſpirit of faith. Theſe men ſhall be able to ſay, <hi>My God ſhall ſupply all my wants;</hi> yea <hi>mine</hi> and <hi>others</hi> that are beleivers, as <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks in the text, for himſelfe and other Saints. God ſhal ſupply <hi>all,</hi> Widdows, Orphans, Priſoners; and <hi>with all;</hi> of which we have abſolute need, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all faile; of what is alſo convenient for us, when it is convenient.</p>
            <p>Firſt, We have abſolute need of grace, <hi>with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out faith it is impoſſible to pleaſe God, Heb.</hi> 11. And God tells us we have <hi>need of patience, Heb.</hi> 10.36. Therefore that God muſt <hi>needs</hi> ſupply: according to his promiſe; <hi>he will poure out his Spirit, Act.</hi> 2. And according to his inſurance, having filled Chriſt, that of his fulneſſe we might receive. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 1.</p>
            <p>Secondly, There is an abſolute neceſſity of what is altogether neceſſary to gracious actings in all conditions. <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.16. <hi>Let us come boldly unto the throne of grace, that we may obtain mercy, and
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:120372:12"/>finde grace in the time of NEED.</hi> And <hi>my grace ſhall be ſufficient for thee,</hi> even in thy wraft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling with Satan, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. Compare diligently, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.13. Therefore this alſo God <hi>muſt needs ſupply.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, That is of abſolute neceſſity that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currs to our natural being and life, whiles God wil have us to be on earth for his ſervice. In this reſpect Chriſt ſaith of outward things, <hi>Your hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Father knows you have NEED of theſe things.</hi> Therefore ſo much of food, of clothes, of liberty, of peace, &amp;c. as whereby we may be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to be, and act according to Gods minde, God muſt <hi>needs ſupply.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, There is an abſolute <hi>need</hi> that God ſhould be glorified by us. He muſt attaine his end. <hi>All things was made for his glory, Revel.</hi> 4. Therefore whatſoever is needful for us to fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Gods glory, that God muſt needs ſupply.</p>
            <p>All theſe are but abſolute neceſſary ſupplyes. But God ſupplyes ſomtimes, <hi>ex ſuperabundan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti, good meaſure preſſed down, and running over:</hi> not onely for <hi>neceſſity,</hi> but for <hi>delight.</hi> And he wil ſo ſupply us at <hi>preſent need</hi> in ſome things, that we ſhall be able out of experience to ſpeake with confidence, of <hi>futures, My God ſhall</hi> ſupply all <hi>needs.</hi> As <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.10. <hi>Who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered us from ſo great a death, and doth deliver; in whom we truſt he will yet deliver.</hi> And <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:120372:13"/>
               <hi>Tribulation worketh patience, patience experience, experience hope.</hi> Paſt mercyes are the <hi>firſt fruits</hi> of future. As the Apoſtle argues, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11. That God hath more mercy for the <hi>Jews</hi> whom he calls the <hi>lump,</hi> becauſe the <hi>firſt-fruits</hi> of the fathers afore the floud, and the Patriarks after the floud were holy by mercy received from God.</p>
            <p>And as God ſupplyes all, with all (as we have ſayd) ſo alſo ſutably to the Saints condition in this world wil he ſupply. For Hel, and the world indeavour to put the Saints into need, and all manner of <hi>wants.</hi> But, ſaith the text, <hi>God will ſupply all your need.</hi> Hel and the world labour to make them poor, and ſcanty, and miſerable; but ſaith the text, God wil ſupply all your need <hi>according to his riches.</hi> Hel and the world, do no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but render them <hi>contemptible,</hi> and igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minious. (But ſaith the text) God wil ſupply ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his riches <hi>in glory.</hi> Hel and the world labour if it were poſſible to <hi>divide them from Chriſt.</hi> But (ſaith the text) God wil ſupply them <hi>by Chriſt Jeſus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> But how wil God ſupply us?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Either ordinarily, or extraordinarily, God is pleaſed (when he ſees good) to uſe means, but he is not tyed to means, method, or manner of acting. When <hi>Moſes</hi> was much with God on the mount he could faſt forty dayes,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:120372:13"/>when <hi>Peter</hi> had a viſion (<hi>Act.</hi> 10.) he forgate his hunger. When <hi>Paul</hi> was in a rapture, he knew not whether he was in the body or no, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore minded not bodily wants. When we conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der our clothing with Chriſts righteouſneſſe, and eternal glory, we ſhall more minde our clothing upon with them, then moth-eatable garments. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. Whiles <hi>Adam</hi> injoyed God, he minded not his nakedneſſe. There are no per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexities can enwrap and hamper and ſeize upon <hi>Pauls</hi> ſpirit, whiles he conſiders Chriſts fulneſſe; through whom he can do all things. <hi>Phil.</hi> 4. A word from Chriſts mouth ſtils him in a great fight of temptations. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. Diſtractions there may be in States, and upon Churches, and every one enquires what wil things come to? But the conſideration of theſe, <hi>Chriſt muſt reign, Pſal.</hi> 2. <hi>Heb.</hi> 2. The four mettalled Image of all humane power oppoſing him, muſt <hi>be broken before him, Dan.</hi> 2. And <hi>Antichriſt</hi> muſt down, as ſure as if down already, <hi>Revel.</hi> 18. <hi>Chriſts Church muſt be ſet up in glory, Revel.</hi> 21. The <hi>Saints muſt rule, chap.</hi> 20: theſe I ſay will qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et our mindes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> But my heart hath many doubtings in it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Doſt thou call him <hi>my God?</hi> and haſt had ſome former experiences what he hath done for thee? then mayeſt thou boldly, as <hi>Paul,</hi> ſay in
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:120372:14"/>the text; <hi>My God ſhall ſupply all my wants:</hi> Yea the ſame God that makes any promiſe wil give to thee lying under the ſerious conſideration of that promiſe, aſſurance through that promiſe, that he wil performe it; and make thee wait till thine eyes ſee it done. In waiting with hope up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on God, a ſoule oft times hath much communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with God. And in this communion, God doth make admirable impreſſions on Saints ſpirits, touching aſſurance, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 130.5, 6, 7. So that if all the world ſhould perſwade them it were in vaine to waite, they could not be taken off. Yea ſome Saints waiting upon God unto, and in great ſufferings, have little leſſe then an impreſſion of Propheſie made upon their ſpirits. <hi>Hus</hi> a <hi>Bohe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mian,</hi> ſignifying a <hi>Gooſe</hi> in his language, ſayd, that if they coſted him in the fire, within an hundred years ſhould riſe a Swan that ſhould carry the cauſe on for which he ſuffered. And according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>Luther,</hi> (ſignifying a <hi>Swan</hi>) roſe up, and did ſo moſt ſucceſſefully. The Martyr that laſt was burnt in <hi>Smithfield,</hi> told the people they ſhould be of a good comfort, for he was perſwaded he was the laſt that ſhould ſuffer under Queen <hi>Mary;</hi> And ſo he was. The world doth not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider this of ſecret impreſſions. And therefore they plot ſometimes great plots, thinking to have the people to ſide with them: But God makes contrary impreſſions, and ſo all falls to nothing.</p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:120372:14"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>Queſt.</hi> When wil God ſupply?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> When his time is come; As he wil not ſtay a <hi>minuit longer</hi> then the fitteſt time; ſo nor wil he act a <hi>minuit afore</hi> the time. But juſt at his time to a minuit he wil do it; <hi>Ioh.</hi> 2. There want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed wine; His mother tells him of it. He anſwers, <hi>his houre was not yet come.</hi> And there were but a very few ſands to run. Thoſe being out, he turns water into wine; which was preſently af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his mother ſpake to him. See Chriſt wil be punctual at the inſtant of the fitteſt ſeaſon to do us good.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> There are many great men and means to hinder thoſe ſupplyes we want.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> What are mountaines before <hi>Zerub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>babel</hi> (ſaith <hi>Zechary</hi>) what can let God to make his way plaine, yea who can reſiſt God when he wil make impreſſions on great mens hearts, that they ſhall not hurt, nor hinder? Both <hi>Laban</hi> and <hi>Eſau</hi> came out in fury againſt <hi>Jacob,</hi> but God made impreſſions on their hearts that they ſhould not hurt him, and they became as tame and gentle as lambs. Plots have been againſt us, as we ſayd afore, by great ones, but God made impreſſions on the Commonalty, that they could not act, nor execute any thing.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> But I am full of unworthyneſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> So thou art in thy ſelfe, but ſeeing it, and acknowledging it, is the way to remove
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:120372:15"/>that, that it be not an impediment. Eſpecially if thou lookeſt from thy ſelf to Gods free mercy through Chriſt, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 130.4. And the text gives thee a ful anſwer. <hi>God will ſupply all thy need ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his riches in glory BY CHRIST JE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>S<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Though thou art unworthy, beleive in, and hope on Chriſt, who is worthy. <hi>He accepts of us in him the BELOVED, Eph.</hi> 1. O therefore that men would not take up Religion in the <hi>outſide,</hi> or in the <hi>Gallantry</hi> of wit, parts, repute, and favour of great men, but in the kernel, faith, hope, communion with God. By theſe to lye in Gods boſome wil quiet, when all helps are ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpended.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> I am in ſuch a ſtate, and condition, as of afflictions, impriſonments, &amp;c. as are quite contrary, to any probability of ſupplys of my wants.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> God to ſhew his wiſedome, and power, and to exerciſe our faith, doth oft times take contrary courſes to ſupply us. As in the <hi>Creation,</hi> being about to make a beautiful lightſome world, he firſt created a <hi>Chaos</hi> lying in darkneſſe; ſo in his <hi>providence,</hi> he works oft by contraryes. <hi>Iſrael</hi> muſt go out of <hi>Canaan</hi> into <hi>Egypt</hi> to be preſerved for <hi>Canaan.</hi> And when at firſt he ſent <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi> to treat with <hi>Pharaoh</hi> to let them goe, things went worſe with them. God
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:120372:15"/>doth of purpoſe ſometimes caſt us into afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and ſeem to hide himſelfe, that we might pray, and beleive, and hope, till he returne and help, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 5. <hi>la.</hi> And for the particular of being in priſon: As touching thy <hi>inward</hi> condition, The Heathen could ſay, <hi>Solus ſapiens eſt liber.</hi> That is, <hi>A wiſe man is the onely free-man;</hi> freer in priſon, then a foole at large, moſt gloriouſly true ſpiritually. <hi>If Chriſt hath made us free, we are free indeed.</hi> Its a brave freedome to go to priſon to be free in conſcience. As touching thy <hi>outward</hi> condition of impriſonment, <hi>Ioſeph</hi> muſt through a priſon be advanced. The Lord wil car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry down <hi>Jeremiah to the Potters houſe,</hi> and there teach him the leſſon he is to learn of free grace, <hi>that God will have mercy, becauſe he will.</hi> Once a priſoner in this place ſpake a glorious ſentence, when condemned to have his head taken off. He ſpake it on the ſcaffold. <q>If there had been (ſaith he) an eaſier way for me to heaven then this, I ſhould have found it: But God would lead me this way rather then no way, thither.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> You have given many faire words, but they ſeeme to be but <hi>notions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Thus our megrom giddy heads think ſubſtances to be but ſhaddowes. I ſay to you, as <hi>Paul</hi> once to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> God or his Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel-miniſters are not <hi>ſtreitned, but ye are ſtreit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in your owne bowels.</hi> Elſe we might come to
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:120372:16"/>that as other Saints attaine to: as a woman of late of mean eſtate ſayd, <q>I want nothing, I have all things in Chriſt.</q> Are theſe onely <hi>noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> which hold forth to us, that which is the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult of all. <hi>viz. contentment,</hi> For God in Chriſt is the onely contentment, which evidently ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears by comparing a poore beleever and a rich unbeleever together: The one hath much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment, the other hath none. Is this a meere <hi>notion? If he ſpared not his own Son, how ſhall he not WITH him freely give us all things, Rom.</hi> 8. And <hi>Pſal.</hi> 37. <hi>I have been young and now am old, yet I never ſaw the righteous forſaken,</hi> &amp;c. Is Gods taking care of crowes, ſparrowes and ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens, <hi>notions?</hi> From thence our Saviour argues, <hi>how much more will God take care of men that truſt in him?</hi> Are thoſe <hi>notions,</hi> that prove moſt real in event? A woman in theſe hard times having loſt her eſtate and yearning over her children, wanting clothes, fel down before the Lord in prayer, mourning thus, <q>Lord ſuch a childe wants a coat, and ſuch a childe wants ſuch a garment, what ſhall I do, my eyes and hopes are upon, and to thee to help.</q> And ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly the Lord ſtrangely provided for them. Two other being in diſtreſſe, the one in torment of paine, the other greatly afflicted with compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. <q>Come ſayd the husband to the wife, if it be the will of God, that thus this extremity
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:120372:16"/>muſt lye upon us, we wil even hire more help to attend, and ſettle to the affliction.</q> And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold preſently the Lord took away the affliction. I have known a ſtock of prayer driven for diverſe years for a mercy; and oft the deliverance came to the birth, and was not brought forth. At laſt it was given in as in a dreame. The thing done, when ſcarce any means uſed.</p>
            <p>Therefore I conclude, Beleeve, pray, hope, and waite on God, and <hi>he ſhall</hi> (according to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible truth of this text) <hi>ſupply all your need ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his riches in glory, by Chriſt Jeſus.</hi> Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
